PROFESSOR: Because this is going to be
an important concept we're going to
build on today, let's remind ourselves
what arc consistency is all about.
So we know how to enforce the
consistency of a single arc.
With arc consistency, what we'd like to
do is we'd like to look at all of
the unassigned variables and make all
of the arcs consistent at once.
And in doing this, we'll be deleting
values here and there from domains in
a way that will detect failure.
So first, let's remember what
it means to enforce the
consistency of a single arc.
Well, here's a single arc.
What does it mean to enforce
its consistency?
What it means is it means we have
to look at the tail of the arc--
remember, we always delete
from the tail.
Remember the constraint satisfaction
police pull this arc over, and they're
going to look and see
what's in the trunk.
So you look at everything in the tail,
and you ask the question, are any of
these values in the tail guaranteed
to trigger a constraint
violation on this arc?
And so we say, well, what about red?
Well, if I chose red at V, then
at NSW I could choose blue.
What about green?
Well if I chose green, I could
choose either, and so on.
So this arc is, in fact, consistent,
because for any value at V, there's a
possibility of avoiding a constraint
violation left.
If we look at this arc, then we can go
through the same reasoning process.
At SA, if we choose blue, we'll be fine,
so the value blue gets to say.
If we flip this arc around, even
though the constraint is not
directional, the arcs that
we make consistent are.
And in this direction, the story
is a little different.
So at NSW, if we choose red, we can
avoid a constraint violation, for
example, by picking blue,
our only choice.
If we choose blue, then we're guaranteed
a constraint violation.
So the way we enforce arc consistency
for a single arc is, in this case, we
would delete blue from
the domain of NSW.
If we then look here, this arc used to
be consistent, but it can stop being
consistent if values are
removed from the head.
For example, the reason why it was safe
to have red at V is because blue
was available.
Blue is not available, and so now if we
choose red at V, then we'll have a
constraint violation guaranteed.
And so we can fix that-- we can
make this arc consistent
now by deleting red.
Now, the big idea with enforcing arc
consistency of the entire graph was if
you look at this particular graph here,
you'll see that because WA is
red and Q is green, NT and SA
both have to be blue, right?
And when we check the consistency of
the arc between SA and NT in either
direction, we'll look at it and we'll
say, all right, well, if I choose blue
at SA, then I'm guaranteed
a constraint violation.
The way I fix that is by deleting from
the tail-- so I delete this--
but now I see that there are, in fact,
no legal values left at SA.
And so I know that this configuration
here, even though I've only assigned
two variables, arc consistency
guarantees me that there is no
solution left, and so I can just
stop the backtracking search.
OK, so as soon as a domain goes empty in
filtering, we know that this branch
of the tree is doomed, and we
can back up in the search.
Arc consistency detects failure earlier
than forward checking does,
but, of course, it's more work.
You have to enforce the consistency
of possibly a lot of arcs.
The important thing here you need to
remember is if a variable X loses a
value, all incoming arcs need to be
rechecked, and that means you might
have to check arcs multiple times.
This will be important.
In addition, there's still a
backtracking search going on, so you
don't run this thing once.
You run it after every assignment at
every step in the backtracking search.
So you run arc consistency
enforcement many times.
OK, well, that's all great.
Arc consistency is much more powerful
than forward checking at a
computational cost, but what
does it do for you?
It doesn't remove the need for
the backtracking search, OK?
After you enforce arc consistency,
you can be in a couple different
configurations.
It's possible you'll have one solution
left, and you'll just be able to see
that every domain has one value, and
you won't have to backtrack again.
That's great.
It also could be the case that you
have multiple solutions left.
It could also be the case that
you have no solutions left
and don't know it.
So, for example, if you look over on
the right and you look at these two
graphs, this one's got
two solutions left.
Arc consistency isn't going to
pick amongst them in any way.
Here, this graph is arc consistent,
but there are no solutions left,
because in order to see the problem,
you have to look at three
variables at a time.
So what went wrong?
The reason why arc consistency in this
bottom case wasn't sufficient to
discover the inevitable failures is
because it only looks at pairs.
So you might think, maybe we need a
stronger notion than arc consistency.
Maybe we need to look beyond pairs.
And there is such a notion.
There's a generalized notion called
K-consistency, where instead of
getting pulled over by this little arc
consistency guy, you get pulled over
by this RoboCop thing.
So what does this K-consistency
look like?
Well, it's basically like arc
consistency, but we can
generalize that idea.
So we can have increasing
degrees of consistency.
So for example, what about
1-consistency?
We didn't even talk about this.
1-consistency is sometimes
called node consistency.
That's the property that every node's
domain has a value which meets the
node's unary constraints.
That's not really useful, because when
you actually solve these things,
pretty much the first thing you do is
enforce your unary constraints.
A unary constraint really is the
same as a restricted domain.
Unary constraints aren't terribly
interesting in that sense.
What about 2-consistency?
Well, we have a name for that.
That's arc consistency.
But let me state it in a way
that will generalize.
Arc consistency says for every
pair of nodes, right-- so
two nodes at a time--
any consistent assignment to one--
OK, so you pick a value for the tail--
can be extended to the other, meaning
there's some value at the head
available that doesn't violate
the constraint.
And that's this diagram right here.
Whatever I do at the tail, there is some
choice at the head that avoids
the constraint.
What about K-consistency?
We can generalize that statement.
We can say arc consistency is about a
pair of nodes, K-consistency must be
about k nodes.
And what it says is if I pick up k
nodes-- and in this diagram here there
are four nodes--
and I take k minus one of them and find
a consistent assignment, then for
any consistent assignment to k minus
1, I have a choice at the kth node
here that will not violate
a constraint.
Essentially, K-consistency says that
whatever you do at the tail-- and
here, the tail's all but
one of the nodes--
you'll be able to safely extend it.
Now, enforcing K-consistency, making
sure that your domains are such that
this property holds, that's tricky.
And just like arc consistency takes a
fair amount of computation, the higher
the k gets, the more computation
you have to do.
For this class, I will assume that you
have mastery of the case for k equals
2-- that's arc consistency--
but the general idea is important.
There's an even stronger notion of k
consistency, and in some sense, this
is really a mathematical distinction.
K-consistency says if you can assign
k minus 1, you can assign k.
For example, arc consistency--
if you can assign one, then
you can assign a second.
Strong K-consistency means
all the lower orders of
K-consistency are also satisfied.
So strong consistency is kind
of a mythical thing.
If you had it, be great.
If you had strong inconsistency,
you'd never have to backtrack.
You'd be living in a wonderful place.
And the reason for this is you
could choose any assignment
to some first variable.
And then you pick another variable.
And because of 2-consistency--
arc consistency--
we know that whatever you do with that
one variable, you can assign
it to the next one.
You've deleted domains in such a
way that that's going to work.
That's arc consistency.
But now you've got two variables that
are assigned without violating
constraints.
And now 3-consistency comes in and says,
well, if you've managed to get
two, I guarantee you that when
you pick up a third,
there's a legal extension.
So great, now I've got three assignments
the don't violate a
constraint, and I can keep doing this
using higher orders of consistency.
So it must be that these higher orders
of consistency are impractical,
because if we had them, then we
wouldn't have to backtrack.
And in fact, this is true.
Full inconsistency is just as hard as
solving the CSP in the first place.
Arc consistency is pretty manageable,
and there are things in between that
are useful.
The most common one is, as you
might expect, k equals 3.
It's something called path consistency,
because you think about
three nodes as kind of forming
a path, right?
Path consistency is much more expensive
than arc consistency, but it
can be very powerful.